嗨，欢迎回到 Startup School 创业课。
Hi, welcome back to Startup School.
我叫 Gustaf，是 Y Combinator（YC）的一名 group partner。
My name is Gustaf and I'm a group partner here at Y Combinator.
今天我要讲的是，如何从和用户聊天，走到获得你的第一批客户。
Today I'm going to talk about how to go from talking to users to getting your first customers.
这是我今天要讲的内容。第一，做那些不能规模化的事到底是什么意思？
Here's what I plan to cover today. 1 what does it mean to do things that don't scale?
为什么这种心态在公司这个阶段如此重要？
And why is this mindset so, so important at this stage of your company?
第二，如何做销售。我会论证，创始人才应该是那个
2. How to do sales. I'll make the argument the founders should be the ones doing
在早期亲自做销售的人。
sales in the beginning.
然后我们会讲一些关于销售漏斗的内容，再讲为什么
Then we'll cover some sales funnel information and then why is it
为你的产品收费这么重要？
so important to charge for your product?
最后，我们会学习如何从你的目标倒推，以及为什么
And finally, we'll learn how you work your way backwards from your goals and why
这很重要。
that's important.
我希望你读过这篇文章，或者说这篇短文，
I hope you've read this article or this essay,
关于创业公司最早期阶段，写得最重要的一篇短文就是
the most important essay ever written about the very early stage of startups is do
Paul Graham 写的《Do Things That Don't Scale》。
things that don't scale by Paul Graham.
Paul 是 Y Combinator 的联合创始人。
Paul is the co founder of Y Combinator.
他在这篇短文里写了 Airbnb 早期的故事。
He published this essay about the early days of Airbnb.
Airbnb 也许是最好的例子，一家成功的 YC 公司就是用这种方式
Airbnb is perhaps the best example of a successful YC company who got their feet off
起步的。很多从没在创业公司或早期公司
the ground this way, many founders who never worked for a startup or an early stage
工作过的创始人，都错误地以为成功只需要一个好产品，
company incorrectly believe that all you need to succeed is a good product
然后增长就会
and growth will take.
自动发生。事实并非如此。
Care of itself. This is not the case.
真相是，好产品几乎从来不是闭门造出来的，
The truth is that a good product is very rarely built in isolation,
而是和你的客户一起打造出来的。
but together with your customers.
结果就是，当你把产品拿给第一批客户看时，
And as a result, it's not actually that good
它其实并没有那么好。
when you show it to your first customers.
换句话说，创业公司不会自己起飞。
Said this another way, startups don't don't take off by themselves.
创业公司起飞，是因为创始人让它起飞，
Startup takes off because founders make them take off
你必须亲手去招揽你的客户。
and you have to manually recruit your customers.
光是在广告网络上按个按钮是不够的。这让人不舒服。
It's not enough to push a button on an advertising network. This is uncomfortable.
创始人们会不断找出各种办法来逃避做这件事。
And founders continuously find many ways to avoid doing this.
最常见的一种是，以为
The most common way is believing
只要多写点代码，或者在你的机器上多做点事，
that you can recruit people by just writing more code or doing more work on your
或者你的机器人，不管你在做什么，就能招来客户。
machine or your robot, whatever you're building.
从我在 YC 的经验来看，我很清楚这其实行不通。
I know this from my experience at YC that this actually don't work.
那我为什么现在要讲这个？
So why am I talking about this right now?
学会销售的技巧只是这门学问的一面。
Learning the tactics of sales is just one side of this of this learning.
最重要的一面，是真正意识到，这一切都取决于你。
The most important side is just really realizing that it comes down to you.
不只是在理论上知道该怎么做销售，
It's not just knowing exactly how to do sales in theory,
而是真的去做，并且真的想成功。
but actually doing it and actually wanting to succeed.
另一个很棒的图示，叫做 Startup Curve（创业曲线）。
Another great visualization is what's called the Startup Curve.
它最初是由 YC 创始人 Paul Graham 画出来的，
This was initially drawn by YC founder Paul Graham
然后由 Trevor Blackwell 标注。
and then labeled by Trevor Blackwell.
你可能之前见过这条曲线。
And you've probably seen this curve before.
大多数公司都会经历类似的过程。
Most companies go through something like this.
它有点像创业公司的时间线。过程是这样的。
It's kind of like a timeline for startups. Here's how it goes.
首先你发布产品。
First you launch.
如今，大多数公司不会在 TechCrunch 上发布，
These days, most companies don't launch on TechCrunch,
而多半是在 Product Hunt、Hacker News 或者其他网络论坛上。
but probably on Product Hunt or Hacker News or some other internet board.
发布带来的那股势头，最终会开始消退，
The launch energy that you get from this launch eventually starts wearing off
因为早期用户总在寻找新的东西。
as early adopters are looking out for something new.
如果你没有立刻获得高留存——做你这类产品的人都没有——
If you don't have instant high retention, nobody does for what you are building,
那你就会进入“悲伤低谷”。
then you will enter the trough of sorrow.
这可能会持续很久，很多公司都死在这个阶段。
This can take a long time and many companies die during this stage.
他们就是放弃了，在测试新东西上动作不够快。
They just give up and don't move fast enough with testing new things.
有些创业公司确实动作够快，不断发布产品的新改进。
Some startups do move fast enough and release new improvements of their product.
他们倾听用户，然后改进。
They listen to users and they improve.
很多公司还是没能更进一步，成了“无能崩溃”的牺牲品。
Many still don't get anywhere further and becomes victims of the crash of ineptitude.
正是那些坚持到底、不放弃的创始人，
It's the founders who stay the course and don't give up
才能走到“虚假希望的摇摆期”，
that reaches the wiggles of false hope
并最终到达 product market fit 的“应许之地”。
and eventually the Promised Land of product market fit.
我们从创业曲线中得到的启示是
The learnings we draw from the startup curve is
在创业初期的每一刻
that every moment in the early days of startups,
决定成败的是创始人
the founders are the ones that make the difference between success and failures.
如果你身处错误的市场，是创始人去切换到新市场
If you are in the wrong market, it's the founders that switch to a new one.
如果你不会做销售，是创始人去学
And if you don't know how to do sales, it's the founders who learn.
所以你必须真的想要它，否则行不通
So you have to really want it, otherwise this won't work.
好，我们先来聊聊销售，以及怎么做销售
Alright, let's talk about sales and how to do sales first.
创始人应该学会销售
Founders should learn how to do sales.
你应该学会销售，因为你需要学会了解你的客户
You should learn how to do sales because you need to learn to know your customer.
与客户交谈和销售，其实是同一枚硬币的两面
Talking to customers and sales are effectively different sides of the same coin
原因和创始人搞不清该做什么产品是一样的
and the same reasons founders can't understand what to build.
他们不明白问题到底是什么
They don't understand what the problem is.
除非你了解客户，否则你不会知道怎么卖
You don't know how to sell unless you know your customers.
第二
2.
学会销售能让你完全掌控创业公司的命运
Learning how to do sales actually gives you full control of your destiny as a startup.
就像你不能把工程外包一样
Just like you can't outsource engineering,
销售必须是创始人 DNA 的一部分
sales has to be part of the DNA of the founders.
有时候你就是必须学会它，因此
Sometimes you just have to learn it as a result,
在你自己学会销售之前，不要去招销售团队
you should not hire a sales team until you know how to do sales yourself.
只有这样，你才知道优秀是什么样子
Only then will you know what good looks like.
如果产品很差，你也做不了销售
You also can't do sales if your product is bad.
而你也不会知道产品很差
And you won't know that the product is bad
除非你先花点力气去卖它
unless you've had some effort in trying to sell it first.
如果你不会卖，别担心，你可以学
If you don't know how to sell, don't worry, you can learn.
这大概是创业公司里最容易学的工作
It's probably the easiest job to learn in a startup.
如果你了解你要解决的问题，如果你对产品了如指掌
If you know the problem you're solving, if you know your product intimately,
如果你懂这个市场，在客户眼里你就是专家
if you know the market you are an expert in the eyes of the customer.
他们会愿意听你说
They will want to hear what you have to say.
最后，对解决客户问题的热爱是很有感染力的
Finally, a love for solving customer problems is really infectious.
如果你对解决这个问题真的充满热情
If you're really passionate about solving this problem,
他们能感受得到，如果你不信我
they will be able to tell if you don't believe me.
这里有几个创始人亲自做销售的例子
Here are some examples of founders who took on the sales job
并且学得非常出色
and Learned to get really good at it.
Tony from DoorDash、Mathilde from Front、Tracy from PlanGrid，还有 Steve Jobs
So Tony from DoorDash, Mathilde from Front, Tracy from PlanGrid and Steve Jobs,
我们直接来看一个例子
let's get straight into an example.
这是 Brex 的创始人，Pedro 和 Henrique
So these are the Brex founders, Pedro and Henrique.
当 Brex 在 2017 年冬季批次参加 Y Combinator（YC）时
When Brex was in Y Combinator in winter of 2017,
他们直接从 YC 批次里招来了前 10 个客户
they recruited the first 10 customers directly from the YC batch.
在 YC 期间，你的好处是身边都是其他创业公司
During YC you have the benefit of being around other startups,
也就是潜在客户
IE potential customers.
Brex 的创始人问自己
The Brex founders asked themselves,
什么样的最小产品
what would the minimum product look like
能做出来并对其他创业公司有用？
that they can build to be useful to other startups?
然后他们就直接去签下这些客户
And then they went straight, straight into signing up those customers.
第一个版本非常非常简单
The first version was very, very simple.
客户只有一张虚拟信用卡
Customers just had a virtual credit card
Brex 的 Henrique 亲自帮每一个客户完成上手
and Henrique from Brex actively onboarded every one of the customers himself.
当然，他们本可以等到有了完整的产品、网站
Of course, they could have waited until they had a full blown a product, a website,
手机应用，这一切都齐全再动手
a mobile app, all of those things.
但他们决定，只要有了真正有用的东西就动起来
But they decided to get going when they had something that was really useful.
这是他们第一张实体卡的样子。在有这张卡之前
This is how their first physical card looked like this. Before they had this card,
他们只有一张虚拟卡
they just had a virtual card.
Brex 联系了他们的 YC 批次同学和其他 YC 公司
Brex reach out to them, their YC batch and other YC companies
这是他们发出的邮件
and this is the email that they sent.
我就读其中一小段
I'm just gonna read a brief portion of it.
嘿，各位，我们为 winter 17 批次的朋友开放内测，有 10 个内测名额
Hey guys, we're opening up a beta for winter 17 batch friends with 10 spots for beta users.
10 个名额。听起来名额有限，所以我该赶紧行动
10 spots. That sounds like there's a limited spot. So I should take actions.
Brex 是一张专注于科技公司的企业信用卡。那说的就是我，完美
Brex is a corporate credit card focused on technology companies. That's me. Perfect.
你其实是直接针对你的客户来写这封邮件
You're actually writing the email directly towards your customers.
我们不需要个人担保
We don't require a personal guarantee.
它能为刚起步的初创公司提供授信。
It can underwrite startups who just got started.
这就是它的价值主张。Brex 的大多数其他替代品都没有这样的东西。
This was the value prop. Most other alternatives to Brex did not have something like this.
那要多少钱呢？免费。
So how much does it cost? It's free.
商家在付钱给我们，所以没有年费。
The merchants are paying us. So there's zero annual fees.
这看起来是显而易见的选择。
This seems like a no brainer.
我觉得这封邮件可能有点太长了，但它确实奏效了。
I would argue that this email is probably a little bit too long, but it did work.
那我们来聊聊怎么写一封出色的销售邮件。
So let's talk about how to write a great sales email.
第一，要简短，最多 6 到 8 句话。
So first, it should be short, max 6 to 8 sentences.
上一页的 Brex 例子可能太长了。
The Brex example on the previous slide is probably too long.
它还是奏效了，但可能太长。
It still worked, but probably too long.
人们没时间读长邮件。
People don't have time to read long emails.
如果你来自学术界，你的习惯会很不一样。
If you're coming out of academia, your culture is going to be very different.
你会写很长的邮件。
You write very long emails.
但在销售的世界里，你要尽量直奔主题、简洁明了。
But in the worlds of sales, you want to get to the point and be brief as much as you can.
第二，要确保语言清晰，不用行话，不用流行词。
2. You want to make sure you have clear language, no jargon, no buzzwords.
直接说清楚你做什么、它怎么运作。然后第三，
Just say exactly what you do and how it works. And then 3,
针对潜在客户正面临的问题。
address the problem that the potential customer is having.
第四，不要用任何 HTML 格式。
4, do not use any HTML formatting.
只用纯文本写邮件，就像写给朋友一样。
Write your email in plain text only like you would written it to a friend.
说明你是做这个产品的公司的创始人。
Say you are the founder of the company who makes this product.
很多人会忘记这么做。
Many people forget to do this.
描述你和你的团队为什么出色。
Describe why you and your team are impressive.
加入社会证明，记住是展示，而不是空说。
Include social proof and remember to show, not tell.
别说你是专家，别说你当专家多少年了。
Don't say you're an expert. Don't say how many years that you have been an expert.
如果你在 YC 的批次里，如果你过去在优秀的公司工作过，
If you're in the YC batch, if you worked at impressive companies in the past,
这些都是你可以加进去的社会证明。
those are other piece of social proof that you can include.
你要加上几条，让读者知道你的来头。
You want to include a couple of these ones so that the reader knows the source.
即使他们不认识，这也能给你赋予一些权威感。
And even if they don't know, you gives assign you some authority.
第六，要附上你网站的链接。网站要简洁。
6, you want to include a link to your website. The website needs to be simple.
上面要有产品的信息。
It needs to have information about the product.
网站不要有很多插画或者付费买的图片。
The website should not have a lot of drawings or sort of like paid for graphics.
只需放上你产品的截图，
It should just have screenshots from your product
以及说明产品功能的要点。
and bullets about what your product does.
有时候发一段短视频也很有效，
Sometimes it works to send a short video,
一个可以嵌进邮件里的 YouTube 视频，
a YouTube video that you can embed in the email
让收件人很容易点开观看。
that's very easy for the receiver to click on and view.
我甚至见过有人用 GIF 动图。
And I've even seen people using GIFs.
那些视频和 GIF 必须立刻切入重点，因为，
Now, those videos and those GIFs needs to get to the point right away because the,
收件人对这个问题会非常熟悉，
the receiver is going to be intimately familiar with the problem,
但没什么时间看两三四分钟的潜在解决方案。
but not really have time to watch two or three or four minutes of a potential solution.
最后，你要加上
And then finally, you want to include
一个请求，比如通话、会议或自助试用，
and ask for a call or a meeting or a self serve,
看什么方式适合你的公司，
whatever is appropriate for your company,
但你发的邮件里必须有一个明确的行动号召。
but there needs to be a call to action in the email that you're sending.
好，我们来聊聊销售漏斗。
All right, let's talk about the sales funnel.
销售漏斗的概念其实相当简单。
The concept of sales funnels is really quite easy.
我觉得人们是被销售人员用的术语搞糊涂了，
I think people get confused by the language the sales people are using,
所以我在这里简化一下，左边我叫它“创始人说法”。
so I try to simplify it here on the left hand side I call it the founder speak.
右边我叫它“销售说法”。
On the right hand side I call it the sales speak.
它们不会完全一一对应，但你能明白意思。
These are not going to be perfectly mapping, but you get the idea.
第一，你要列一份你打算联系的客户名单，
So first you want to make a list of customers you plan to reach out to in say else
这在销售里叫开发潜在客户或获取销售线索。
is called prospecting or lead generation.
我们就叫它“列名单”。
We'll just call it make it the list.
你可以用 Google Sheets 之类的工具来做这份名单。
And you can use Google spreadsheets or something like that to make this list.
然后我们要给他们发邮件、发 LinkedIn 消息，或在 LinkedIn 上加他们，
Then we want to send them an email or a LinkedIn message or add them on LinkedIn or
或者任何适合联系这些人的方式。
whatever is the appropriate way to contact these people.
之后，你要根据邮件的回复，
After that, you want to schedule and run a demo or a meeting from
安排并进行一次演示或会议。
that response to the email.
然后你要谈定价，最后把他们成交为客户。
And then you want to talk pricing and then finally close them as a customer.
最后一件不能忘的事，是在你成交之后，
The last thing which you should not forget is after you've closed them,
你还得引导他们上手，确保他们真的开始使用你的产品。
you still need to onboard them to make sure that they start using your product.
如果这一步成功了，留存也不错，
If this is successful and you have good retention,
那就能带来长期收入。
that could lead to long term revenue.
如果你忘了最后这一步，就会出现大量流失，
If you forget the last step, then you will have lots of churn
因为大家其实不知道怎么用你的产品，
because people don't actually know how to use your product,
这在早期产品里很常见，
and this is common with early products
因为它们一开始很难上手。
because they are not easy to onboard in the beginning.
这不是你会花大量时间去优化的东西，
This is not something you spend a lot of time optimizing,
所以一定要把引导上手作为这个流程的一部分。
so make sure that you do the onboarding as part of this process.
回到我做的那些 Google 表格，
If you go back to the Google spreadsheets that I'm making,
我把所有信息都填进去，你应该从简单开始，
that I'm putting in all the information, you should start simple,
但要有几列来记录你在跟踪的信息。
but you should have some columns of things that you're tracking.
比如行业、公司、职位、姓名、邮箱，也许还有 LinkedIn。
So industry, the company, the title, the name, the email, maybe the LinkedIn.
一开始有这些就够了。
This could be enough to start with.
很多 CRM 软件都自带这些分类或这些字段。
A lot of CRM software comes with these categories or these columns.
用一个简单的 CRM 软件是个不错的主意，
It's pretty good idea to kind of use a simple CRM software, um,
来实现同样的目的。
to kind of accomplish the same goal.
但关键在于提前把这份功课做好。
But the key thing here is doing this work up front.
我见过很多 YC 创始人，当他们积累到上千条这样的信息时，
And I've seen a lot of YC founders that when they are getting to 1,000 of these,
他们会想，哦，这是个很简单的活儿。
they're like, oh, this is a very simple task.
我其实可以外包出去。我觉得这行得通，
I can actually outsource this. And I think that can work
前提是你很清楚自己外包的到底是什么。
if you know exactly what it is you're outsourcing.
把这些信息存下来，将来会对你很有帮助。
Storing all this information is going to be helpful for you in the future.
现在我做好了名单，也理解了销售漏斗。
Now, I made my list. I understand this. The sales funnel.
那我该去找谁，又该怎么排优先级，
So who should I be going after and how should I be prioritizing
在做主动联系的时候？
as I'm doing the outreach?
关于销售，这是我最重要的建议。
Here is my most important advice when it comes to sales.
你的第一批客户应该是最容易搞定的那些。
Your first customers should be your easiest.
现在不是去啃最硬骨头的时候。
This is not the time to bite off the hardest 1.
专注于最容易的那些。
Focus on the easiest ones.
我的意思是，你在做销售时，
What I mean by that is you should try to do sales,
要尽可能让销售过程对自己来说轻松。
make the sales process as easy for you as you possibly can.
创业公司真的没时间去追每一条销售线索。
Startups don't really have time to chase every lead.
外面有很多销售线索。
There's a lot of leads out there.
你不必全都拿下，真的不必，你还这么早期。
You don't have to pick all of them. You really don't. You're so early.
你可以只挑那些最有可能成交的。
You can pick only the ones that are the most likely to close.
最好的做法是拥有一个大的销售管道，
The best way to do this is to have a big pipeline,
也就是你给很多潜在客户发邮件，
but that means a lot of people that you're emailing of potential customers
然后随着你收到回复、约到会面。
and then as you're getting responses and you're getting to meetings.
开始优先处理那些最可能成交的人。
Start prioritizing those who are the most likely to close.
你大概能从他们对你资格筛选问题的回答中看出来，
You can probably tell from their answers to your qualifying questions during the
在销售通话里，避开那些进展缓慢的，
sales call, avoid those who are moving slow,
也别害怕放弃某些客户。
and don't be afraid of letting customers go.
别害怕放弃某些客户。
Don't be afraid of letting customers go.
我的意思是，如果有人拖着你打了两三次电话，
What I mean by that is that if someone is dragging you along, two or three calls,
你完全可以说，认识你很高兴，我也学到了很多，
you can always be like, it's been great getting to know you and I've Learned a lot,
但我们不如半年后再聊。
but we should talk again in six months.
这么说完全没问题。
That's totally fine to say.
第二，卖给你认识的人会比卖给陌生人容易，
2, selling to people you know is going to be easier selling to strangers,
所以你应该充分利用你的人脉。
so you should take advantage of your network.
第三，卖给创业公司是最容易的一类，这一点我反复验证过，
3, selling to startups is the easiest category and I've I've Learned this on
尤其是在 YC 公司里，特别是那些想卖软件的公司。
and on again with YC companies specifically the want to sell software.
事实证明，越大的公司官僚流程越多。
It just turns out that bigger companies have more bureaucracy, more processes.
他们甚至有专门的部门负责跟你谈判，
They even have a specific department that is in charge of negotiating with you,
这会花很长时间。
and that takes a long time.
而创业公司完全没有这些东西，
And startups don't have any of these things
因为他们没时间去搞出这些东西。
because they don't have time to create these things.
这对他们来说不是优先事项。
It's not a priority for them.
所以创业公司的决策链条很短。
So startups have short decision making lines.
你往往能马上找到决策者。
You can often find that the decision maker right away
在做outreach时，你也不用经历一个很麻烦的流程。
as you're doing the outreach and you don't have to go through a difficult process.
这就是为什么卖给创业公司更容易，
That's why startups are easier and
这也是为什么我们建议大多数公司去卖给创业公司。
that's why we recommend most companies to sell to startups.
这就引出了我的第四点。
That leads me to the fourth point.
大多数人不是早期采用者。
Most people are not early adopters.
我一直对我合作的YC公司反复强调这一点。
And I keep saying this to the YC companies I work with all the time.
你之所以要发几百封邮件，原因不是
The reason you have to sell, send hundreds of emails is not
大多数人会很生气，然后说，
that most of those people get really upset and be like,
我真不敢相信你居然给我发邮件。
I can't believe you emailed me.
比如，我很喜欢另一个替代产品，但我讨厌你的产品。
Like, I really love this alternative product, but I hate your product.
事实并非如此。
That's not what's going on.
你发邮件的大多数人只会直接归档，他们根本不在乎。
Most people that you email are just be like archive, they just don't care.
他们不会去尝试一个新产品，
They're not gonna try a new product
无论它是通过你的LinkedIn还是邮件找上门的，
that comes in through your LinkedIn or your email,
而且他们可能整个职业生涯都不会去尝试新产品。
and they might not be the people that try a new product at all in their career.
这是大多数人。而另一些人，
That's most people. Some other people,
我记得我在Airbnb工作时就是那样的人。
I remember being one of those people when I worked at Airbnb.
我很喜欢创始人给我发邮件介绍新产品，
I would love when founders emailed me with new,
介绍新产品，而我会是那个去注册试用的人。
new products and I would be the one signing up for them.
所以我在Airbnb工作时，如果你是一家创业公司，给我发邮件是很棒的。
So when I worked at Airbnb and you were a startup, emailing me was great.
我就是个早期采用者，我喜欢尝试新东西。
I am an early adopter. I love trying new things.
我不介意尝试新东西带来的风险。
I don't mind the risk of trying new things.
所以你每发一封给普通公司的outbound邮件，很可能，
So for every outbound to an average company that you send, you'll most likely,
在一封普通的outbound、普通的邮件、普通的LinkedIn消息里，很可能，
most likely on the average outbound, average email, average LinkedIn,
触达的是一个不是早期采用者的人。
reach someone who is not an early adopter.
要触达早期采用者，你就得发更多的outbound消息，
To reach early adopters, you just have to send more outbound messages
因为你根本没时间去说服任何人成为早期采用者。
because then you don't have time to convince anybody to become an early adopter.
你得找到早期采用者，一开始就直奔他们去。
You have to find the early adopters and just go for them early on.
别管其他所有人，你根本没时间去说服他们。
Don't worry about everybody else, you just don't have time to convince them.
我们来聊聊收费。
Let's talk about charging.
作为创始人，你会很想
It's attractive for you as a founder
你的公司免费提供产品，
and for your company to offer your product for free,
提供免费试用或不付费的试点项目，这些形式五花八门。
offer free trials or unpaid pilots and these things come in many shapes and forms.
但是，如果你不向客户收费，
However, if you don't charge your customers,
他们就不是客户，你也就没有一家公司。
they are not a customer and you don't have a company.
客户付钱给你，是你在为他们提供真实价值的有力信号。
Customers paying you money is a great sign that you're providing them real value.
所以你要克服因为价格而被拒绝的恐惧，
So you should resist the fear of getting a no because of price
而不是在他们不想付钱时去纠结价格该定多少。
instead of figuring out what the price should be if they don't want to pay.
你在第一次通话或第一次会议的资格甄别过程中就能了解到这一点。
And you learn this during the qualification process in the first call or first meeting.
如果他们不想付钱，这就是一个明确的信号，
If they don't want to pay, that's a great sign
说明你应该转向下一个客户。
that you should move on to the next customer.
再说一次，放弃那些看起来不合适的客户，
Again, fire the ones who seem like they're not good fit,
转向下一批客户。
move on to the next customers.
免费试用在消费者中很常见，但如果你仔细想想，
Free trials are common for consumers, but if you thought about it,
大多数面向消费者的免费试用会先要信用卡，然后我们就忘了，
most consumer free trials ask for the credit card upfront and then we forget
结果照样付了钱。
and then we pay anyway.
这是因为这样做效果最好。
That's because that actually works the best.
这在B2B里更好的做法不是免费试用，而是退款保证。
The B2B version of this is a better one than a free trial is a money back guarantee.
也就是我们向你收费，如果你不满意，
So we charge you if you're not happy,
你可以在30天或60天内拿回退款，或者更好的是，
you can get the money back in 30 days or 60 days or even better,
你可以选择退出年度合同，
you have the ability to opt out from the annual contract,
只付一个月的费用，而不是整年的费用。
just pay for one month instead of the annual fee.
但在B2B销售里，你不应该提供免费试用。
But you should not offer free trials in B2B sales.
改用退款保证，并提供可以退出的选项，
Go for a money back guarantee and go for the ability to opt out instead,
不断提高价格，直到客户开始抱怨，
increasing your price until your customers are complaining,
但仍然付费，这才是正确的做法。
but still paying is the right way to go.
好，我们来聊聊大多数创始人都会搞错的事情。
All right, let's talk about the thing that most founders get wrong.
我已经说过很多次了，但有几件事
I've said this many times, but there are a few things
是大多数创始人会搞错的，而这就是其中之一。
that most founders get wrong and this is one of them.
用你的销售漏斗从目标倒推，从而一步步
Working backwards from your goal with your sales funnel in order to work your way
从目标倒推，比如说签下两个客户，
backwards from a goal of, say, two signed customers,
你要明白，销售漏斗的每一步都会有流失。
you have to understand that each step in the sales funnel is going to have a drop off.
当你还没开始做销售时，
When you haven't started sales yet,
你并不知道这些流失比例是多少。
you don't know what these drop off percentages are.
也许你以前没做过多少销售，不知道自己不擅长什么。
Maybe you haven't done a lot of sales before, you don't know what you're not good at.
也许你很擅长发邮件，但很不擅长成交，或者反过来。
Maybe you're really good at sending emails but really bad at closing or vice versa.
你不知道这些。
You don't know that.
所以在你发这些外联邮件时，
So as you're sending these outbound emails,
你需要做记录，开始追踪所有这些转化。
you need to take notes and start tracking all of these conversions.
在这个例子里，我发出500封外联邮件或LinkedIn消息。
In this example, I'm sending 500 outreach emails or LinkedIn messages.
我有50%的打开率。
I have a 50 percent open rate.
也就是说250人会打开邮件，5%会回复。
That means 250 people will open the email, 5 percent will respond.
大约是20个潜在客户。
That's about 20 potential customers.
其中50%会从回复转化为演示，
50 percent of those will convert to demo from the response,
也就是说我做了10场演示。
which means I'm doing 10 demos.
这挺不错。但我做演示不太在行。
That's pretty good. But I'm not that good at doing demos.
演示里最后只有两个成了客户。
Only two end up becoming customers from the demos.
那是20%。我敢说你们大多数人根本没追踪这些数据，但你应该追踪。
That's 20 percent. I bet you most of you don't even track this data, but you should.
如果你追踪这些数据，你就大概知道要花多久才能拿到
If you track this data, you will have some idea of how long it will take to get to
10个付费客户。
10 paying customers.
如果你不追踪，别人就很难给你反馈，告诉你什么
If you don't track this, it's very hard for someone to give you feedback of what's
有效、什么无效，对吧？
working and not working, right?
这就像你在发布一款新产品时，
It's just like when you're launching a new product,
你会想要一些指标和用户数据，来判断它是否有效。
you want to have some metrics and some user data to be able to tell if it's working.
做销售时，你也想拥有这些数据。
When you're doing sales, you want to have this data.
如果你有这些数据，别人就能给你反馈，告诉你哪里做得好
If you have this data, people will be able to give you feedback on what you're good
以及哪里需要改进。
at and what you need to get better at.
我的建议是用一款简单的销售CRM软件，
My advice is to use a simple sales CRM software
它能自动追踪这些转化率。
that tracks these conversion rates automatically.
我们来看第二个例子。
Let's look at the second example.
这就是大多数创业公司的情况，
This is how it looks like for most startups,
甚至包括我在这一批里合作的公司。
even the ones that I work with in the batch.
在第二个例子里，我发出100封外联邮件。对我来说感觉挺多了。
In the second example, I'm sending 100 outreach email. It feels like a lot to me.
如果我沿用上一个例子里不变的转化率，
If I keep the conversion rates constant from the previous example,
我最后实际上一个客户都没有。
I actually end up with zero customers.
于是创始人得出的结论是：销售对我不管用，
And the conclusion the founders draw after this is that sales is not working for me,
我应该去做营销、SEO，或者别的什么，或者做转介绍之类
and I should just do marketing or SEO or something else or referrals or something
听起来更吸引人的事。
that sounds attractive.
这完全错了。你根本没有数据来下这个判断。
This is simply wrong. You don't have the data to make that call.
你做的外联根本不够，没法得到销售漏斗里真正准确的
You did not do enough outreach to actually get to correct conversion rate
转化率百分比。
percentages in your sales funnel.
所以答案是：你发的邮件太少了，你没有数据，
So the answer here is you sent too few emails, you don't have the data,
你不能得出销售不管用的结论，即使
you can't draw the conclusion that sales is not working even
你现在一个客户都没有。
though you have zero customers.
而这正是创始人一次又一次犯的错误。
And this is the mistake that founders do on and on and on again.
所以总结一下我刚才讲的内容，
So to summarize what I just went through here,
你不知道自己的销售转化率。
you don't know your sales conversion rate.
所以你需要一个CRM来追踪它。
That's why you need a CRM to keep track of it.
第二，因为你不知道谁是早期采用者。
2 because you don't know who is an early adopter.
在外联销售中会有大量流失。
You have a lot of drop off in the outbound sales.
这让外联销售最终成了一场数字游戏。
That makes outbound sales ultimately a numbers game.
成功的创业公司会意识到并内化这一点。第三，
Successful startups realize this and internalize this. Three,
你不可能从10个销售线索里成交5个客户。
you cannot close five customers from 10 leads.
这不可能。你需要多得多的外联，多得多。
It's not possible. You need a lot more outbound than that, a lot more.
而不幸的是，大多数创始人不会从这个销售漏斗
And unfortunately, most founders don't work their way backwards from this sales
倒推，也不会做这个练习。
funnel and they don't do this exercise.
结果就是，他们销售做不成功，还不明白原因。
And as a result, they don't succeed as sales and they don't really know why.
我在Airbnb的一位朋友，Lenny Rachitsky，
So a friend of mine from Airbnb, Lenny Rashidski,
他写了一个很棒的博客，还写过一篇很好的文章，讲YC
he writes an excellent blog and he wrote a great blog post about how YC
以及一批非YC的B2B创业公司。
and a bunch of non YC B2B startups.
让他们的销售 go-to-market 策略跑起来。我推荐读一下这个，
Got their sales go-to-market strategy going. I recommend reading this,
他 newsletter 里的另一篇文章。
another post from his newsletter.
这是我读过的最好的文章之一。
It's one of the best ones I've come across.
里面有很多他从真实公司收集来的真实数据，
It has a lot of real data that he collected from real companies,
其中很多是 YC 公司。
many of them being YC companies.
在这个例子里，第二列，
So in this example here in the second column,
Lenny 描述了其中一些公司最初的销售方式。
Lenny is describing the initial sales motion of some of these companies.
可以看到，一些早期公司，比如 Amplitude、Stripe、Front，
As you can see, some of the early ones like Amplitude, Stripe, Front,
他们一开始就在发外联销售邮件，就像我们前面讲的那样。
they were doing outbound sales emails just like the one we described to get started.
那些创始人在起步时都亲自发这些销售邮件。
Those founders were doing those sales emails as they get started.
另外一些被称为 product-led（产品驱动）。
Some of the other ones were called product-led.
product-led 可能不只是发外联销售邮件，
Product-led could mean something else than just doing outbound sales,
但它不意味着有一个庞大的销售团队，
but it doesn't mean having a big sales team
通常也不意味着做营销、SEO 或别的东西。
and it usually does not mean doing marketing or SEO or something else.
product-led 指的是产品本身，
Product-led means something that product itself is, is,
某种程度上在驱动增长。
is sort of like driving the growth.
在做演示时，你的目标是拿下第一批客户。
As you're running the demo, your goal is to close your first customers.
你要在演示中一开始就问很多问题，
You want to ask a lot of questions upfront in the demos
而且应该由创始人来做演示，
and it's the founders who should do the demos
因为你最了解产品，也了解客户的痛点。
because you are the one knowing the product and you know the customer pain points.
这里有三个带来客户的 YC 邮件例子。
Here are three examples of YC emails that led to customers.
具体细节你们之后可以自己看。
So I'll let you guys look at the details of these afterwards.
但这是一封外联邮件，带来了每年 72,000 的合同。
But this is an outbound email that led to a 72,000 a year contract.
这一封是非常具体的邮件，最终拿下了 Algolia 这个客户。
This one led is a very specific email that led to landing Algolia as a customer.
第三个例子是这一封邮件，
And this third example here is the one email,
同一封邮件为他们带来了 22 个不同的客户。
the same email that got them 22 different customers.
好，我再总结一下。
Alright, I'm gonna summarize this again.
大多数创始人最大的错误是外联做得不够，
The biggest mistakes that most founders do is they don't do enough outreach
因为他们没有从目标倒推，
because they don't work backwards from the goal,
总以为除了销售之外的东西能解决销售问题。
believing that something else than sales is gonna solve your sales problem.
外包销售是错的，你应该自己做。
Outsourcing sales is wrong. You should do it yourself.
而且你要在第一通电话里筛选客户。
And you need to qualify your customers during your first call.
这里是我推荐的一些工具。
Here are some of the tools I recommend.
工具真的非常非常多。
So there are many, many, many tools.
这可能是你做销售时可用工具里最大的品类之一，
This is perhaps one of the biggest categories of potential things you can use
在你做销售的时候。
as you're doing sales.
但我推荐 Apollo.io、Close.com（原名 Close.io）、Pipedrive 或 Hunter。
But I recommend Apollo.io, Close.com, formerly called Close.io, Pipedrive or Hunter.
.io。这些都是很好的工具，可以当作简单的销售 CRM 使用，或者 Hunter。
.io. These are great tools that you can use either as a simple sales CRM or Hunter.
你可以用它从 LinkedIn 获取联系人或可发邮件的潜在客户。
You can use to get contacts or potential people to email from LinkedIn.
这里还有两个额外的资源。
Here are two additional resources.
有些人会问我要书。
Some people ask me for books.
通常没什么好书，
Usually there aren't good books,
但我确实遇到过一本觉得很不错的。
but there is actually one that I come across I find really good.
它叫 Founding Sales。另外我还推荐 Lenny's Newsletter.com。
It's called Founding Sales. And then I also recommend Lenny's Newsletter.com.
当然，创业公司还有别的增长方式，
There are, of course, other ways that you can grow as a startup,
但我学到的真相是，就算你最终像 Airbnb 那样，
but the truth that I've learned is that even if you end up with, say, like Airbnb,
增长来源是口碑、Google 搜索、推荐，
where the sources of growth is word of mouth, Google search, referrals,
还有 Facebook 广告。
Facebook advertising.
如果这些是你增长策略的最终状态，
If those are the kind of end states of your growth strategy,
那也不是 Airbnb 起步的方式。
that's not how Airbnb got started.
他们并不是靠 Google SEM 或 Google SEO 起步的。
They didn't start by running Google SEM or Google SEO.
推荐计划并没有带来最初的 2000 个客户。
The referral program did not bring in the first 2000 customers.
他们做的是那些不能规模化的事，
They did things that didn't scale
这些事和他们规模化之后做的事不一样。
and they look different than the one they do at scale.
所以很多公司直接扑向所谓的可规模化增长
So a lot of companies are resorting straight into what's called scalable growth
渠道，那些他们听说有效的渠道，规模化时确实有效，
channels, the channels that they've heard work, which is true at scale,
但这和你刚起步时不是一回事。
but that's not the same thing as when you're getting started.
在这张幻灯片里，我大致勾勒一个粗略的想法，
So in this slide, I'm outlining kind of like just a rough idea of like,
就算最后 Google SEM 和 Google SEO 是规模化时有效的方式，
even if it turns out the Google SEM and Google SEO is what's gonna work at scale,
你也需要在网上找到另一个地方，这些人在那里
you need to find another place online where these people
你要通过 SEM 和 SEO 触达的那批人。
that you're gonna reach through SEM and SEO.
是那些在网上主动表明自己需求的人。对吧。
Is identifying themselves online. Right.
如果你想做 SEM，情况可能和 Google 不一样，
And that might not be the same as Google if you're trying to go after SEM,
SEM 就是搜索引擎营销，
which means search engine marketing,
因为有竞争，成本可能会很高。
it's going to be expensive probably because there's competition.
如果你想做 SEO，那需要很长时间。
If you're going after SEO, it's going to take a long time.
如果你的增长靠的是产品驱动、病毒传播或推荐，那就先用个人人脉，
If your growth is, say, product LED or virality or referrals, then personal network,
通过个人人脉、卖给你的同事，就是起步的办法。
selling through your personal network to your coworkers is the way to get started.
当然，如果你走的是销售路线，那就该老老实实做销售。
Of course, if you're doing sales, you should be doing sales.
早期销售和大规模销售其实没太大区别，
It doesn't change very much, like early stage sales to large scale sales basically
无非就是我刚才讲的这些事，
means all the things that I just described here,
只不过是由一支上百人的销售团队来做，配上更多自动化、更多工具、更多指标，
done by 100 people in a sales team with more automation, more tools, more metrics,
但本质是一回事。
but it's the same thing.
如果你的产品适合做线上营销，
And if your product is set up to do online marketing,
那通常也不是大多数人起步的方式。
it's not usually how most people start.
为什么？
Why?
因为你没法轻易和人交流。
Because you can't really easily talk to people.
你没法从用户身上学到东西。
You can't learn from users.
如果你的头一千或头一百个客户是通过 Google
If the first thousand or first hundred customers are brought in through Google
和 Facebook 带进来的，这些人往往
and Facebook, those people are not the kind of people
不是那种你能轻松约上 30 分钟电话的人。好，
that you can easily get on a 30 minute phone call with. Alright,
今天就讲这些。谢谢大家。
that's all I had today. Thank you everyone.